http://www.rlssdirect.co.uk/help/privacy-policy.php

Home
Products
NEWVouchersRookie LifeguardLifesavingLifesaving SportWork Based QualificationsPool ManagementLifeguarding (Pool & Beach)RLSS UK Trainer & Instructor KitEmergency Response & First AidRLSS UK MerchandiseOpen WaterWarehouse ClearanceCatalogueMembershipDrowning Prevention WeekCommunity ResourcesFin2Fit
Courses
Donate
Resources
Membership
Help
Login or Register
Search
Product Categories
NEWVouchersRookie LifeguardLifesavingLifesaving SportWork Based QualificationsPool ManagementLifeguarding (Pool & Beach)RLSS UK Trainer & Instructor KitEmergency Response & First AidRLSS UK MerchandiseOpen WaterWarehouse ClearanceCatalogueMembershipDrowning Prevention WeekCommunity ResourcesFin2Fit
Privacy Policy
About us
The Royal Life Saving Society UK (“RLSS UK”) is the drowning prevention charity (charity number 1046060) and is the UK’s leading provider of water safety education and qualifications. RLSS UK is also the National Governing Body, recognised by Sport England, for the sport of life saving. RLSS UK’s
website is
http://www.rlss.org.uk/
RLSS UK is structured as two limited companies and 47 membership branches located across the UK. The two limited companies are:
RLSS U.K. Enterprises Limited (trading as RLSS Direct), with registered office at Redhill House, London Road, WORCESTER, WR5 2JG, United Kingdom (company number 02559199). RLSS Direct stocks, sells and fulfils a range of products to help support the delivery of vocational and non-vocational awards and qualifications mainly via the website
https://www.rlssdirect.co.uk/
IQL UK Limited with registered office at Redhill House, London Road, WORCESTER, WR5 2JG, United Kingdom (company number 03719774). IQLUK is the lifesaving qualification awarding body offering OFQUAL regulatedand non-regulated vocational training programmes and qualifications. Through IQL UK, there are more than 90,000 RLSS UK pool lifeguards trained in the National Pool Lifeguard Qualification (NPLQ) and around 95 per cent of all pool lifeguards are trained by RLSS UK.
RLSS UK is the controller of all personal data processed by the charity, the two above operating companies and the 47 membership branches.
Data Protection Officer
RLSS UK’s Privacy Officer is:
Jason Ellis
RLSS UK
Redhill House
London Road
WORCESTER
WR5 2JG
(t) 0300 3230 096
(e) gdpr@RLSS.org.uk
Personal Data Processed by RLSS UK
RLSS UK collects, stores and processes personal data for several purposes, mainly: membership administration, financial accounting, marketing and the administration of the charity. The detail of this is described in the table below.
Type of data
Purpose
Legal Basis
Retention period
Volunteer / Club Positions
Volunteer Application Forms
Administration
Performance of a contractSome processing may be legitimate interests*
2 years
Club Officer Roles
Administration
Legitimate Interests*
Visible records of those is currently in position – Hidden records for historic purposes.
No retention period records stay forever
Volunteer complaints
Management of complaints
Necessary for compliance with a legal obligation
Necessary for the purpose of legitimate interest
3 years form the end of the complaint procedure
Members/Candidates/Trainers
Membership list comprising names, addresses, telephone numbers
Membership administration and communication
Performance of a contract and some processing may be Legitimate Interest*
2 years after membership ceases
Course candidates – Community based awards comprising names, addresses, telephone numbers, email addresses and course results
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be Legitimate interest
2 years after all membership and awards have expired***
Course candidates – Non - Regulated awards comprising names, addresses, telephone numbers, email addresses and course results
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be Legitimate interest
2 years after all membership and awards have expired***
Course candidates – regulated awards comprising names, addresses, telephone numbers, email addresses and course results
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be Legitimate interest
7 years from the day of assessment***
Course candidates – other organisations awards/qualifications comprising names, addresses,
telephone numbers, email addresses and course results
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be Legitimate interest
7 years from the day of assessment***
Trainer Assessor candidates/paperwork – names, addresses, telephone numbers, email addresses and course results
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be legitimate interest
???
Instructor and Instructor Tutor candidates/paperwork
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be legitimate interest
???
Candidate certificate data held on Credcert– name, address, email address
Award administration
Performance of a contract and some processing may be legitimate interest
Non- regulated awards and community awards – 2 years from the date of processing
Regulated awards and awards from other organisations – 7 years from the date of processing
Honours Nominations
Administration of the honours recognition and rewarding Process
Legitimate Interest*
No retention period records stay forever
Membership benefits
To send information which is included within your membership of RLSS UK including details about competitions, conference, honours, events and any updates to awards and qualifications
Performance of a contract
2 years after all membership and awards have expired***
Queries or complaints data
To maintain a record of your interaction with RLSS UK regarding your query or complaint
Legitimate Interest*
3 years from the end of the complaint procedure
Completed reasonable adjustment forms
To maintain a record of any reasonable adjustment granted to the candidates
Legitimate interest*
2 years from the end of activity by the individual
Children's Data
Children under the age of 16
Administration of award data
Consent from a parent or guardian or another adult acting in loco parentis
2 years after all membership and awards have expired**
Athletes and Officials/Coaches/Team Managers
Event attendees
Administration
Performance of a contract
Legitimate interests*
1 year
National Records Database
Deleted once the course has started
* Note the legitimate interest may include:
retaining records to properly administer and manage your membership or awards and qualifications data with us.
In the case of Club Officer Roles – data may be required in relation to complaints or claims and to ensure the effective management of any disciplinary hearings, appeals and adjudications.
In the case of Event attendees/Elite athletes and Officials/Coaches and Team Managers we have a legitimate interest to provide you and other members of our organisation with a safe environment in which to participate in sport.
National records database – we have a legitimate interest to maintain the records of those competitors who achieve a National record within Lifesaving events
Honours nominations – we have a legitimate interest to maintain the records of those individuals who have achieved an RLSS UK Honour for historical purposes.
Queries or complaints data – legitimate interest to provide complaint handling services to you in case there are any issues with your membership/club/event etc
** Note that certain information collected for the purposes of personnel administration are a contractual and statutory requirement which are necessary to enter into a contract of membership.
Failure to provide this information may result in our inability to offer membership.
*** Note that certain candidates may have achieved an RLSS UK Honour and will remain on the system indefinitely as this is classed as data of historical purpose
Data Sharing
RLSS UK shares personal data with the following organisations:
Organisation name/category of organisation
Purpose of the sharing
Data Storage Location
RLSS Commonwealth
To aid RLSS Commonwealth with data on UK Members
RLSS UK
Official Organisations
We share the personal data of some of our membership necessary because of a legal obligation with official authorities such as governing bodies, insurance companies, police, child welfare
All personal data is stored in secure UK data centres operated by organisations with ISO 270001 certification.
Disclosure & Barring Service
To disclose a copy of a person’s criminal record
All personal data is stored in secure UK data centres operated by organisations with ISO 270001 certification.
RLSS UK Branches
We share the personal data of some of our members from time to time with members of their local Branch
All personal data is stored securely by members of the RLSS UK Branch in which the data is disclosed
Sub-contract Processing
RLSS UK uses sub-contact organisations to process personal data under a written contract which defines that they must comply with stringent data privacy requirements. RLSS UK only employs organisations that comply with the provisions of the General Data Protection Regulation. These organisations are audited to ensure compliance. RLSS UK’s processors include:
Organisation name/category of organisation
Nature of the Processing
Data Storage
Digital Service Providers (APT Solutions and Galtec)
We employ specialist companies to host our database and facilitate our IT services meaning that they potentially have access to any personal data collected via the channel they manage for us. These organisations are data processors and governed by legally binding contract set out in GDPR
All personal data is stored in secure UK data centres operated by organisations with ISO 270001 certification.
Stratum APT
Secure hosting of RLSS UK database
All personal data is stored in Secure UK data centres operated by organisations with ISO 270001 certification
Mailchimp
To facilitate the sending of RLSS UK emails
M Leach Jewellers
To facilitate in the engraving of medals and trophies for sporting events, championships and honour events
Claremont cars
To facilitate airport transfers for Board of Trustees, event volunteers
Laerdal
Supply of medical therapy and training products
Data Augmentation
RLSS UK uses augmentation services to satisfy its legal obligation to ensure the accuracy of personal data being processed by using, for example:
Royal Mail Postal Address File (PAF) to update redirected addresses and to ensure address accuracy and completeness.
Profiling
RLSS UK does not use profiling
International Transfers
We will neither transfer nor process personal data outside the United Kingdom, nor will we permit personal data to be transferred or processed outside the United Kingdom by a third party, unless it is under one or more of the following conditions:
the territory into which the data are being transferred is one approved by the UK’s Information Commissioner;
the territory into which the data are being transferred is within the European Economic Area;
the territory into which the data are being transferred has an adequacy decision issued by the European Commission;
the transfer is to the United States of America and the recipient is registered under the EU/US Privacy Shield scheme;
the transfer is made under the unaltered terms of the standard contractual clauses issued by the European Commission for such purposes;
the transfer is made under the provision of binding corporate rules which have been approved and certified by the European Commission;
the transfer is made in accordance with one of the exceptions set out in Data Protection Legislation
Secure storage of data.
All personal data are stored in secure UK data centres operated by organisations with ISO 270001 certification.
Your Rights
You have the following rights concerning your personal data:
Right of access
You have the right to obtain confirmation from RLSS UK as to whether or not personal data concerning you are being processed, and, where that is the case, access to that personal data.
Right to rectification
You have the right to oblige RLSS UK to rectify inaccurate personal data concerning you. Taking into account the purposes of the processing, you have the right to have incomplete personal data completed by providing a supplementary statement.
Right to erasure (right to be forgotten)
You have the right (under certain circumstances, but not all) to oblige RLSS UK to erase personal data concerning you.
Right to restriction of processing
You have the right (under certain circumstances, but not all) to oblige RLSS UK to restrict processing of your personal data. For example, you may request this if you are contesting the accuracy of personal data held about you.
Right to data portability
You have the right (under certain circumstances, but not all) to oblige RLSS UK to provide you with the personal data about you which you have provided to RLSS UK in a structured, commonly used and machine-readable format.
You also have the right to oblige RLSS UK to transmit those data to another controller.
Right to withdraw consent
If the lawful basis for processing is consent, you have the right to withdraw that consent by contacting
gdpr@rlss.org.uk to arrange for a withdrawal of consent form to be sent or by downloading from the RLSS UK website.
Right to object to direct marketing
Where your personal data are processed for direct marketing purposes, you have the right to object at any time to processing of your personal data for marketing, which includes profiling to the extent that it is related to such direct marketing.
Rights in relation to automated decision making and profiling
RLSS UK does not perform any automated decision-making based on personal data that produces legal effects or similarly significantly affects you.
Your right to lodge a complaint with a supervisory authority
If you wish to exercise any of your rights concerning your personal data, please contact RLSS UK’s Data Protection Officer at the address shown above. If you are not satisfied with the response you receive you have the right to lodge a complaint with the supervisory authority. In the United Kingdom this is:
Information Commissioner's Office
Wycliffe House
Water Lane
Wilmslow
Cheshire
SK9 5AF
(t) 0303 123 1113
(e) casework@ico.org.uk
